and that's it.
Huff.
Yeah, it's not a bit of a bit of a bit.
Okay.
How much?
Here's the next step.
All right, welcome back.
So, oh, I have to put this on.
So many connections.
The Wi-Fi, not the Wi-Fi, but the connection
to where I host the website for the course is working.
So I'm going to run this off of my machine,
and I'm going to hope that it works well.
We're going to do our best.
So I'm also going to silence my phone.
There's more options.
So, here we are.
We are at our last chunk of new material for the final, anyway.
I might cover something next week that has to do with Java and thread safety,
which is somewhat interesting from a programming language's perspective.
So I think that's a bit more effective.
Plan for tonight will be to cover this new material that we're going to do.
A lot of JavaScript.
So I give you a warning in advance, I'm not a real JavaScript guru.
So some of the things on the slide I may have to stop and we may research.
Well, together, so we'll learn together.
Usually I get a little bit more because of the holiday yesterday.
I didn't get any extra time to sit down and go through the whole presentation and make
sure I was up on everything.
The other thing I discovered is some of the slides that I've published are sort of falling
off the page and I need to fix that.
But because I can't send the updated slides to the server, then I have to run it off my
machine.
be an updated set of slides that comes out at some point. Probably when I get home, probably
tomorrow. I'll let you know when I publish those. So for now, we're going to work off
my machine. And then this new material shouldn't take more than a couple hours, so we'll go
through that. We'll take our break in there, wherever it makes sense, and then whatever
time we have left tonight we can start continue through the study guide and do some of those
review problems hopefully that makes sense all right why don't we start though with the quiz
i do want to go over the quiz so let's do that the time snuck up on me today
so i didn't log into d2l so bear with me while i log into d2l
Oh, and before I get too far, did anybody have any homework questions from the last homework that was due yesterday?
I'm going to assume that if nobody says anything, that everybody's happy with and understands everything there is to understand about the homework.
That's the assumption, right?
If not, speak now, or speak next week, or come to office hours, any of those things.
So if we go into quizzes, oh yeah, before I start, remember you have this extra credit
opportunity if you do the program assessment just for doing it, I'll give you two points
on your final grade calculation.
So when I checked, oh yeah, 15 of you have done it.
There's about 30 something of you.
So it's free extra points.
does help DePaul figure out what it might need to adjust about the
curriculum I'm not really involved in that they just said here here are the
questions can you give them to your students so I will probably be sharing
your answers with professor Mitch who I think is in charge of that department
chair you get two points for doing so so make sure you do that it will help all
All right, so quiz 7.
All right.
So, the question that we're going to get has to do with the different variables.
So, Fd, e, and E, so it asks you about the different variables.
It will figure out which type each of the variables are.
So, the variables will be said to have static type, and
then the dynamic type, but remember the dynamic type doesn't really refer to
what the variable is, it refers to what the variable refers to live in your running program.
So, if we take a look at this code,
we see we have our class animal and then we have a class bird that extends animal.
And we're overriding to string so that when we call to string,
which essentially is what happens when we try to print things,
we get different output.
So let's start with I'm going to go in the order of the variables abcdef.
And our options are going to be static type animal and the dynamic type animal.
Static type bird and dynamic type bird.
Static type animal and dynamic type bird.
By the way, notice we don't have static type bird and dynamic type animal.
Why is that?
Anybody?
A bird can't refer to an animal, but you can refer the other way around.
You can't, like, upcast a subclass.
Right.
So the compiler is going to make sure that you compile a code, the types agree.
At runtime, you can only have a type that's valid for that reference.
So that's why we don't see, as Matt was kind of explaining, we don't see that we have static-type bird and dynamic-type animal.
Because you can't just point to a supertype in a reference.
That's a lower-down type.
When I say lower-down, I mean lower-down in the type hierarchy.
So variable A, what do we got?
What's our static type and what's our dynamic type?
Hopefully this is pretty easy.
animal, animal. So animal, animal, that's 1. So I'm going to go ahead and fill that in.
Okay. How about variable b? Also pretty straightforward, right? Bird, bird. So variable b is going to get 2.
For bird, bird. Okay. How about variable c? Animal, bird, right? It's pretty clear, right?
We have animal here and we're instantiating a bird,
and so that's pretty obvious, right?
So static type animal, dynamic type bird.
All right, so that's three.
Okay, letter D, sorry, letter D.
So this one, what's our static type?
Animal.
Why is it animal?
What in your words why would it be animal?
I just think about it as placement.
As placement?
Yeah.
Whatever is before the equal sign is the static type.
whatever is technically after the equals sign.
So whatever happens during runtime is the dynamic.
So it doesn't get the equals sign.
It's not like a sign that what happens after
the equals sign immediately.
I know what you mean.
Yeah. I'm waiting for you to let me respond to that.
So yes, so essentially the way I would say it,
this is what the compiler sees.
The compiler sees that D,
as the programmer you're saying D is an animal. So the compiler will also make
sure that like whatever you're putting here is compatible with that. So when you
do the equal sign, it'll make sure of that. But it'll just look at the static
type of B and see that that's bird and see it will also see that bird extends
animals so say yeah that's valid, I can go that way, sure. So you're not wrong
It's just like the way you explained it, I was like, yeah, that sounds right.
I wouldn't use those words.
But yeah, you're on the right track.
You got that intuition, right?
So, right.
So, D is going to be static type animal, and then dynamic type, what's it going to be?
Bird.
And that's because, at the time we do the assignment, the thing that B refers to is
actually really a bird.
Right?
That's why.
If b referred to maybe some other kind of bird,
like the subclass, if there were another one, like duck,
then the dynamic type would be duck.
But we don't have duck here.
But it's going to look at the actual type at runtime,
and that's going to be the dynamic type.
So this was static type animal, dynamic type bird.
So that would be three.
Okay.
So, then we have E. So, this is where it starts to get tricky.
What does the compiler think about E?
Think, doesn't think, right?
What does the compiler, what information is available to the compiler about E?
Static type is Animal.
Okay, Matt, tell me why you think so.
Because the static type is implicit since it's left off so
it's gonna be whatever the static type of C is, which is .
Yes, I wouldn't use the word implicit because implicit has a very
specific meaning in Java about resolving, not Java, Scala,
about resolving like things.
So it's inferred.
That's the feature of Scala that we're talking about is type inference.
The feature of Scala called Implicits is something else.
That's why I'm just cautioning about language,
about what we're using.
So C static type is animal.
And so the compiler says, OK, E static type is going to be animal.
Now what about its dynamic type?
Bird.
And that's because at runtime you're
thing that C is actually referring to is bird.
So animal bird.
So animal bird is 3.
And then for f, this one, we got f.
We're going to create this val f, and then we're going to set its value equal to b.
So what is the static and dynamic type of this one?
Bird, bird.
Okay, Dylan, tell us why.
For the same reason as the last one,
It infers from B that B is a bird.
It infers from the variable that you've declared or the value that you've declared
that the static type is bird.
So it says, OK, F static type is going to be bird.
And then B is going to be dynamically bird.
So this one, bird, bird.
So that's 2.
Now, to test our knowledge and make sure I didn't mess up,
because I'm not perfect, let's throw this
into Scala's interpreter in the Ripple.
And just one thing to be super clear about,
we're both compiling and running this code
when we put it in the Ripple.
So there was a discussion in Discord about some Java code.
And somebody was saying, well, it doesn't execute.
I'm like, well, it does execute.
It just throws an exception.
So you got to be careful just not getting the answer
or the result you think you're getting
doesn't mean that the code doesn't compile and execute.
If it compiles, it will execute.
It may crash for an exception or something.
But that's a runtime answer.
So when you're working with languages like interpreted
languages or languages like Python, especially.
And I'm not real up on the right way to explain it.
But Python is a more dynamic language,
and so it's doing all this stuff.
I don't know that it actually compiles.
It may, but I'm not sure.
So let's type this in here.
All right.
So a is an animal.
E.
C is an animal.
D is an animal.
He ends up being an animal statically because that and on the right, it shows you what the
denominator type is.
So that looks like what we said.
Does anybody think I messed up?
This is possible.
I think it's good.
Okay, so that's that first question.
All right.
Now we have this code in Scala.
So true or false, the values returned by a.f and b.f are the same regardless of how the
methods f are implemented.
So we have class a with a method f returning an int, no parameters, class b extending a
with f being overwritten.
That's what we have here.
Then we have instantiated an A and a B, and notice our static type here is A and our static
type here is B, but both times our dynamic type is going to be B. And if I call A dot
F which, when I call A dot F, which implementation of F do I actually call given this code?
The one in B, the one defined in B. Because, do you know why?
We talked about last week, it's called dynamic dispatch.
So we're dynamically going to dispatch to the actual runtime implementation
of that method for the runtime type.
So since the runtime type is always going to be B,
when we call A.F, we're going to get the one implemented in B.
You already follow that.
So then the question, the values returned by A.f and B.f are the same regardless of how the methods F are implemented.
That would be true.
Okay.
Now we have something similar, but this time it's in C++.
So here we have class A.
We have a virtual method F.
We have class B, where we have F overriding the one from class A.
And this little syntax here is what we say extends in Java and or Scala.
So here we have pointers to some objects that we were instantiating.
And then we ask if I dereference my pointer.
Or, I'm not dereferencing my pointer, sorry.
If I'm taking the pointer and finding the f method for each of these.
Which version of f will I invoke for each of these?
And they may be different, so for each one, which one?
Both call class B.
We're both going to call the implementation in class B.
Okay, thanks Matt.
Tell us why?
Using C++ when you have pointers for
dynamic type like the subclass as long as the methods are marked virtual and override in the
base class and subclass respectively it'll call the dynamic one if you don't mark them
virtual or override or you don't create a pointer you just create a like it's on the stack yeah
it will call whatever the static type would have been.
Yeah so the answer here is true, and yes Matt is correct.
The next one however we don't have that keyword virtual.
So this time we don't have the keyword virtual, and we are accessing a and b through pointers
and we're accessing the F method, what's the answer to this question?
False.
So, based on what Matt just said, we can build on that and say, because this is not
virtual, we're not dynamically dispatched.
So in Java and Scala, we get dynamic dispatch by default.
In C++, we do not, unless those two conditions are met.
We're accessing the thing through a pointer and the method is declared virtual.
We need both of those things.
So this one, the answer should be false.
This time we're back to virtual.
But notice how we're instantiating the mouse.
We're instantiating this way.
So we're not accessing through a pointer.
We've just invoked the constructor.
We didn't say, well, in the last one, we said new.
When you say new, then you're getting memory allocated on heat.
And here, you're not getting memory allocated on heat.
That actually doesn't matter as much because you could be passing a pointer to another
function or something.
In this case, virtual, yes, but we're calling a.f and b.f.
So in this case, which f is invoked for each of those?
A and b.
You think it's b?
Oh, you think it's a.
calls A's implementation and B dot F calls B's implementation.
Ah, but I think that's not correct.
But maybe I'm wrong.
I think that because these are not accessed through the arrow operator,
you're going to get A's implementation of that.
Even though B is statically typed as B?
Oh, I missed that, thank you.
Good catch.
No you're right, you're right.
Static type is B so it resolves at compile time.
So yeah you're right.
I missed that that was not an A, I thought that's why A.
Yeah.
So the values returned by a.f and b.f are the same.
So I think the answer is false.
Yeah, I think so.
Because in this case, we're gonna dispatch to a's f.
Because even though it's virtual, we're
calling it with this dot notation.
And then in b's case, we're gonna dispatch to this one.
So the values returned by a.f and b.f are the same, false.
So thank you for catching.
Okay, now we're into Scala.
And in this case, make it a little smaller.
So we have two questions, does the code compile?
And if so, how many times is the method f in class A called?
So what do we got?
Well, we have class A with an app and class,
and notice it calls this .g.
And we have a g here.
We have class b extending class A and
we're overriding both f and g.
And so the question is, does the code compile?
Use your mental compiler.
Or do what I did when studying to confirm.
First, I would say try to make sure you take an educated guess as to whether it compiles.
right?
And then put it into the interpreter and see if it
compiles or the REPL.
And it does compile.
So notice that it's safe to override, right?
It's safe to override.
Here you're calling this dot g.
g is defined in a, so you're always going to be safe, right?
It's not as if this G were missing
and we only were adding G without the override.
If we were, then it wouldn't compile.
So yes, it compiles.
And then how many times is the method F in class A called?
So we start by passing minus 5.
So this is where sometimes I like to actually do this
with a call stack.
Maybe it's helpful.
So we're in main and we call F.
And we have what do we have?
We have a.
And a is pointing to this instance of b.
b doesn't have any data, it just has some methods on it.
So when we call a dot f,
we'll dispatch dynamically here, right?
So we're going to go into B's, B dot f, and we have an n, n is minus 5.
And so we say immediately, super dot f of n.
So what does super do?
It calls the super class one.
Right, parent class, super class.
So then we're going to call a dot f.
And this time, and we pass the same thing, right?
Oh, no, the plus one happens after, right?
So call with the minus five here.
Now we're in a dot f, so then we check to see if n less than zero,
that's true, right, because n is minus five.
So then we're going to do this dot g.
G. So which G do we get?
Class A.
You think it's the one in class A?
Is everybody
is that what you were saying?
I think it's the one in B.
Okay, tell us why.
Because when you did new
B, it's like
a B
I guess, so I think this refers to B.
But I could be wrong, I forgot.
So
the runtime type is B, right?
So if the run type type is b and in this language we have dynamic dispatch,
we're dynamically dispatching to b's implementation of f.
Everybody follow?
So we go into b's implementation of f.
No, into b's implementation of g.
Oh, g.
Thank you.
Sorry.
I had the right class and not the right method.
Thank you.
V dot G.
There we go.
So in B's G, our N is still minus 5.
Right?
And then in B's G, we call this dot F with minus N.
So what are we going to get?
This dot f is going to call which one?
Dynamic dispatch again.
Class B.
One in class B. So we have B dot f.
And again, we're B dot f with minus 5.
Uh oh!
No, I guess it passed my number.
Dark...
Say again?
It gets passed 5.
Because it's negating it, isn't it?
I'm not looking closely.
That's what you're saying.
Yeah yeah yeah.
It's five, okay cool.
Okay, so now, in b's f with five,
we call this dot f.
So which one is I gonna dispatch to?
You're framed back, we're in f right now, right?
We're in f. Okay. Sorry. Thank you. Super dot f. So now we're going to go here. I have to keep looking at the picture. That's why I drew the picture.
No.
So super dot f.
Am I right, Matt?
Yeah.
Okay, and now n is going to be 5.
5.
Okay.
And now this time when we do this test, we take the else case, right, because 5 is bigger
than 0.
So we're going to call this dot g.
So which G again?
No.
My brain is dry.
Else N.
If, else N.
I didn't read carefully.
Thank you.
You're on the ball tonight.
So we're just returning N.
Okay, so there's no more stack frame.
So we return five.
Right?
And actually, when I put that code in there, how am I got?
Because we forgot to do the plus 1.
The plus 1.
The extend at the F or .
And did that happen twice?
Yes.
Yeah.
So we had, let's see.
We haven't added the one yet.
It's on .
That's right.
So we're returning 5.
OK, very good.
Thank you.
So we're returning 5.
And now we're back in B.F.
we got 5 back, so we're back in b.f, and here we're returning that thing we got back plus 1.
So now we're returning 6. So we're returning 6 back here to b's g, and this is just going to return 6.
So we return 6 back to where we came from, so now we're in a's f and we have 6.
And we return that, there's nothing else we're adding.
So we go back to where we came from which is b's f again and now we're adding 1 again
and we're returning 7.
And we're returning 7 and we're going back to main.
and that's why it prints out seven.
Very good.
I was like, huh.
And then in my head, I just said, we're done,
but we weren't done because we needed to return.
Caused.
I'll leave that there because the next one's gonna miss.
Okay.
So, code compiles.
And then, oh, I already erased it.
So how many times is method f in class a called,
how many was it?
Twice.
I remember that from last night when I tried out the...
The other thing that if you're not sure, what I would encourage you to do is you can also,
that was weird, random applause in the end of the class.
It was because we got it right.
What?
It's because we got it right.
Yeah, they were happy for us.
So I was going to go in here.
So it asked the question, how many times is the method f and a called?
So what I would do here is if you're not sure,
you can do print line a.f and then you'll see it prints out a.f twice.
Then you can confirm your understanding by doing that.
But this way that I did it on the board is important for
you to understand, like how it,
Does the call stack ring?
And then computers go so fast that we
tend to forget what they're doing
because we focus on other details.
All right, here's the next one.
Does this code compile?
No.
I agree with that.
Why does this code not compile?
Because A's method for G calls this.f, but it has no f method.
f is defined in class B, but is not an overridden method.
So you'll get some sort of reference failure type.
Yeah, the compiler version.
Compile it.
Yeah.
Right.
So you would, if it were to allow that.
So what if, okay, well, if I have a B, though, I might have an F.
Right?
That's my counter.
Yeah, but A doesn't know about that.
A doesn't know about F.
And it must be the case that when the compiler is looking at this,
the compiler has to be able to find an F defined for A.
Now, you might override it, right?
You might declare it abstract.
But if it doesn't exist as far as A is concerned,
then the compiler is like I can't figure out how to dispatch, how to write the
instructions to have this dispatch properly. So this will not compile. Code
does not compile. And you can confirm your understanding again by trying this.
And when you see this E008, not found error, this is the compiler.
This is not, it's not even getting to the point where it's trying to execute because
the compiler just says the code U type doesn't make sense in this language.
And it's unlike compilers for C. Compilers for C and C++ only use types for offsets.
Maybe that's not true for C++ exactly, but for C, for sure, it's only for offsets.
Okay, so that's that one.
a ScalaCode snippet, we have a method f in a,
we're calling this.f.
We have a method f in b,
and we're overriding that,
we're extending class a and we're overriding it.
And again, we're checking our value of n
and then we're calling super.
So if we call super we're gonna dispatch here all the time,
If we call this, we might dispatch here if we're dynamic type A.
We might dispatch here if we're dynamic type B.
That's this type of here.
Then we might, let's see.
Are we ever calling G?
We're calling G here, but are we ever calling G?
No.
Okay, so should we do it on the board like before?
I don't remember the answer offhand.
It's not going to compile?
But why?
A has no g.
A has no g?
At the bottom, it's static type a.
Oh!
But because it's static type a.
Yeah.
So what Matt is saying is look, a static type is g.
The compiler will say there is no such thing.
So, yeah, we can't even do it on board, right?
So let's see.
It should fail to compile at that line.
Yeah, it won't compile there.
Now, if we tried to do this without calling the method,
it would compile.
But it was just that last statement, or the last expression,
no statements in Scholarman, that last expression.
There's no such thing.
Good catch.
Code does not compile.
All right, so this one.
Does the code compile?
And this time, it asks, how many times is f called?
I don't remember.
And that's, I'm going to go backwards this time,
and I'm just going to try this.
It does compile.
OK, that's good.
So if we look at it carefully, we'll see that.
So we call it a.g.
Our static type is b, though.
So as far as this code is concerned, the compiler says,
well, there's a G on a B statically.
So I'm good.
Inside G, we have calls to this.f,
so it would either dispatch here or dispatch, well, no,
you're always going to be in a B, right?
You're never going to dispatch up there, right?
Here in class A, if you're executing this.f,
You may, if you have just an instance of an A, a dynamic type A,
you would just call yourself F. Over here, you might call superclass F.
Did I get all the places where it would dispatch?
I think I got them all.
And then how many times, so should we do this one on the board?
Let's do this one on the board.
All right.
So we have a new b, and we're referring to it
in a variable called a of type b, static type b.
And here's my main.
So when I call a.g, I'm actually invoking b's g.
So when I'm in b's g, I have an n,
And that's going to be, what did I say, minus five, right?
And then I called this dot f.
So which f am I calling?
One in b.
One in b?
Are you passing five?
Oh, did I flip?
I'm not flipping the thing.
I'm not reading the code here from you.
So we're passing five.
Thank you.
Because we're negating.
So then I'm going to b.f.
And then, all right.
So if n less than 0, false.
So we're not going to call super.
We're just going to return 5.
So, this comes off and we get five back.
Oh, you know what?
Let me leave that there, just for a minute.
This was five.
The reason I did that was because I wanna just exit out
so we can keep track of it,
cause later on we're gonna talk about how many.
So, let's call.
So.
So I return the five, and I go back to B is G, and I return the five,
and then I go back to main, and the result should be five.
So the question asked, how many times is the method F in class A called,
and the answer should be zero, right, because we never win it.
All right, let's see.
So last night I was two TV shows in and tired from running around all day,
and I got one question wrong.
And this time I got them all right, with your help, of course.
Because last night I did read that one line correctly
and I remembered the minus signs.
So there we go.
All right.
So this quiz, I would encourage you to make sure you understand the answers.
It's not just like, can I copy and paste the code in REPL and see what it does?
It makes you understand why.
And if you don't understand why, like if you know it compiles, but you don't know how many
times the method is called or why, then put some little print line statements and trace
it.
I would also encourage you to get used to drawing these for yourself.
Whenever I look at that stuff.
I mean, this stuff is, when you're working in a real world
scenario, your IDE will tell you all the possible ones then
you have to, all the possible implementations of class.
And then you have to sort of reason about, well,
which instance am I in?
And usually, there's only a small handful of instances.
And there's enough context for the program
that you're working on, so you know which one you're doing.
I don't have to do these contrived examples at work.
So I never have to reason about it like quite this way.
But it's good to understand.
OK.
All right.
Cool.
Well, let's dive into our new stuff for tonight.
And again, bear with me in advance, because it's JavaScript.
And I am going to use this other browser, which
runs within my Windows subsystem for Linux.
So it could be a little slower.
Oh, before we get to JavaScript, though,
we're going to talk about nested classes.
This is more in my wheelhouse, where I'm used to.
We're gonna talk about nested classes, what they are, and why they matter for us, for
Java and so on.
So, let's think about functional features in an object-oriented language.
So we're gonna talk about nested and anonymous classes and what those are.
and we're going to use object-oriented concepts
to implement lambda expressions.
So you're used to seeing lambda expressions in Java, maybe now.
Let's talk about how that all works on the covers.
So back in Java 1.0, so we're talking 1996.
I was a senior in college.
It came out, and my professor was using it
to teach us multi-threaded stuff in operating systems,
even though it simulates operating systems.
But this was the state of play in Java 1.0.
So if we think about wanting to do like what we do now in a map function,
if you have this array of integers and you want to do what we call mapping over that array of integers,
this is what you would have to do.
you would have to actually iterate over the array and
access each element of the array and then call this apply method.
So we call it apply for a reason.
And how would this work?
So we would define this thing called IntMapper.
So see we have this parameter M, which is an IntMapper.
And IntMapper is gonna have the logic for the map function.
You know, when we have map today, we take each element and we have a parameter, which
represents the element, and then we apply the function to that element and then we turn
the result again.
We're doing this all in one logical operation where we're saying we're going to take every
element and we're going to transform each element and we're going to just think about
it at that level.
That's why they're called higher order functions.
So in Java 1.0, you would have to declare an interface like this with an apply method.
You would have to implement that like this in a class that you define.
And so to use it, if you're in your main program, you have your array.
This is just a wrapper, by the way, for the elements.
You want to fill an A, oh sorry,
this is just comments saying,
you would have code here to fill up the array.
Then in here you're passing in an instance of the named class.
This is a named class and you have
to instantiate it and pass it in like that.
Java 1.0, that was the world.
The question is can we avoid explicit named classes?
So, in Java 1.1, they came out with this.
So this time, over here, up here in this big blank space, I don't have a concrete named
class that I wrote as a program.
What I did was I have this anonymous class here.
So I can say new and the name of the interface, and then I have to provide the implementation
of the method that's declared by the interface.
So this was a little bit better
because now you could declare
your int mapper function here
in line, sort of, if you will.
And then in Java 1.8,
we can reduce...
So if we can just go back to Java 1.1,
from Java 1.1 all the way up to Java 1.8,
that was what we had to do.
and Java 1.8, we now could use a lambda.
So this is the syntax that we see here.
And it adds this idea of a functional interface here.
So what's a functional interface?
Well if you look at the Java definition of functional interface,
you see this.
So a functional interface, and actually there are many of them.
So you could look in here, there are different kinds of functional interfaces,
But there has to be one single method on a functional interface.
In this case, we're saying that this functional interface,
the method we're going to define in the interface, we're going to call it apply.
We're going to take a parameter t and we're going to return some type t and
return some other type R.
So, we have this.
And if you look in java.awt.event, runnable, callable,
all of these are functional interfaces.
So now I can say, all right.
I think our previous example, what
were we doing in our functional interface?
We were adding one.
So in all of these, we were taking whatever we got.
We add one, and that's what we return.
So we can now instantiate a function like this,
And we're required, of course, because we are,
this is new function, right?
So this is this interface here.
We're required to pass the parameter of some type and
then return some other type.
In this case, t and r are the same type, which is totally fine.
So this was how we had to do it.
Well, this is the same as that, put it that way.
I don't remember when functional interface came around.
I think it showed up in one point.
I don't think they had it before one point.
So what are non-functional interfaces in Java?
So any event interface that has multiple methods.
So you can't use lambda notation.
So for a mouse listener, this wouldn't compile
because what this annotation does is
it tells the compiler that you need to have the same shape,
we often say when we talk about types,
the same shape as a functional interface,
which we've defined there.
So the fact that we have two methods here
make it so that it can't be a functional interface.
This doesn't actually tell us anything about the parameter,
like this is a void, this is a mouse event.
A functional interface can be, these can be any types.
Void is one possible type, mouse event is another possible type.
The fact that you have more than one thing here makes it so
that it can't be a functional interface.
And the compiler will yell at you.
So these are all implemented using nested classes.
So the compiler supports nested classes, but Java, the JVM, does not.
So what actually happens is, remember how I said Java tries very hard to be compatible with the past?
So rather than change what is available in the JVM, the compiler actually, when you do that thing
where you create either a lambda or an anonymous class,
the compiler actually will create a new named class for you
with a dollar sign in the name.
So then the question arises, should we
allow nested classes with free variables?
What could that be useful for, and what
do we have to be careful about?
So anonymous classes cannot have explicit constructors.
That's the big thing, I guess, to be careful about.
All right.
So here's Java 1.8.
So for closures, we can replace explicit constructors.
So what happens in this code?
So, variable x is gonna be free in our nested class.
So here's our nested class because this is where our new appears, right?
And this is the, that's not correct.
Our nested class is here because that's where lambda appears.
The new isn't.
You're constructing a new thread, but
you have to pass it in the sense of a run tool, right?
And so this is actually, I actually have not been a Java programmer in
in a system that use lambda, so that's why I always get tripped up.
I don't do this very often.
So what's happening here is you're constructing a new runnable, right?
So this is a nested class.
This is an anonymous class.
And x inside of this lambda expression here is free.
There's no definition of x.
So it has to get x from somewhere else.
So it ends up getting bound to the variable x in line 3.
And this whole concept, this whole idea is really useful for GUI programming and
listeners because you always have to respond to events.
So the output here ends up looking like this.
We're actually copying i into x and
And then that x is getting accessed here but
which line in that code up there seems useless.
Why do we need x at all?
Does it make sense to do this?
That's a question that I'll answer.
So we tried it without, right?
And we just said, let's try doing this.
We're gonna just print our eye.
Compiler will reject it.
And I remember when I first saw this compiler message,
I have seen this compiler message anymore,
back when I was a Java programmer.
So, local variables referenced from an inner class must be final or effectively final.
What the heck does that mean?
Well, it has to do with the way Java creates a closure for that free variable i.
So now i is free in here.
So you don't need to do...
So back to, so just to finish this.
So that's why on the previous slide,
you had that int x equals i
because that's effectively final.
Notice the reason why it's effectively final
is because first you create it
and then you assign i,
the value, whatever i is,
to that x.
But nowhere else are you changing x.
Every time your for loop,
the body of the for loop executes,
you get a new x.
So when it creates a closure to make this work, it makes that x part of that closure.
It copies it yet again, actually.
So that's what's happening.
So that's why compiler rejected this.
But if you look at a language like Python or Perl, this is totally legal.
And the behavior you're going to get is that.
So range is going to give you I think 1 to 4.
It might be 0 to 4.
I don't know.
0 to 4, alright.
I'll take it.
But by the time the threads start up, you notice for each iteration you're starting
a new thread.
By the time the threads start up that i has been set to 4, which is the last value of
in the range, and there is some latency involved
in the thread goings, the threads going,
and so that's why you see all these fours.
So the closure here is sharing I across the different threads.
And you need a closure again because I
is free inside of this method body.
Some languages will allow mutable variable.
So here's Python.
Here, what we're doing is we're actually copying i into something else called x.
And then we're using x here.
So both i and x are free, oh sorry.
No, both i and x are free.
but because this is gonna execute before
it's gonna get the .
I'm not a Python expert, but you know.
So this is what you would get.
In Scala, this works as we might expect.
So this is different than Java.
So in Scala, the closure mechanism is gonna treat I
as effectively final in the loop body.
So it's actually gonna make a copy
underneath the covers for you.
Because, again, it's gonna execute on Java,
So it's gonna build a class with a cloven.
So here's our summary.
Object oriented languages support nested anonymous classes.
And then functionality of restricted scope.
Syntax resembling lambda expressions of functional languages makes
these classes convenient to use and
classes with methods that have free variables in need.
And the close.
So, one thing that's interesting about all this stuff is,
if you're using a Lambda in Java, there is a new,
the last few versions of JVM, there's
a new instruction for that.
Scala has not yet used that instruction.
A lot of times, the makers of the JVM are trying to Oracle,
I guess owns it now, right.
used to be sun when I was starting out.
But they like to create new features
in their implementation to support things like this.
But so far, last time I checked, and maybe as Scala
continues to develop, they'll eventually
start making use of that.
So this new instruction would make it more efficient
to be able to use that.
I think it's called Invoke Virtual.
But don't quote me on it.
And you don't have to remember that.
When the Scala compiler sees this
and it's compiling to Java byte code,
it's actually creating a nested class.
So the whole point of this line of discussion
on nested classes is to show you how closures are.
And that was our summary.
But here's just a little example here where we have a GUI.
And in our GUI, we have a button with a go.
And as we press it, it increments.
But the point of this slide actually put this into my IDE
just to kind of play around with it.
But the point of this slide is to just show you
that this part here, it makes coding this
a lot easier to have lambda.
So if you think about Java version 1.0,
I would have had to create a new class myself.
I would have had to hand code the whole thing.
And then after 1.1 and after, I could do it anonymously here,
which is a little bit better.
But you still have to type that whole new thing, right?
So what this does is it simplifies all of it.
The compiler will check when you're creating this lambda that you're
If you actually look at AddAction, let me actually bring it up.
I think I have it up.
I didn't start my ID.
When you are calling AddActionListener,
there is some interface that it's using here.
I think it's called ActionListener.
I can't remember.
I'm not a Java GUI programmer.
I've never done that.
I'm getting my ID slowly.
Let's see how I was doing this this afternoon.
Yeah, so if I go to add action listener, I have to wait for it to load its world and
cache everything, the IDE actually reads the code and then creates a whole picture of
so you can navigate around.
That's button, okay.
Yeah, that's what I want.
It's taking its time.
There it is, actionListener.
So, our addActionListener method takes an actionListener.
An actionListener is this interface
that extends event listener.
It has a single method, actionPerform, with actionEventE.
So it's not required that you use the annotation
to say it's a functional interface.
It's just helpful for the compiler.
If you don't use it, though, it's perfectly fine.
It will just make sure that if you use a lambda,
that whatever your, whatever, when you use it lambda,
you're basically implementing a single interface as a single method with whatever
type here and whatever type there.
There's only one input type.
So actually, it might be fun to run it.
So we'll run it.
And we get this little window up here, which I can use.
And I can click it.
And it should increment this thing.
So that's just to illustrate that.
So here in this code here, oh, this is showing you right.
So if I compile this code, this would
be in some class called run2.java, some file run2.java.
And it would be within the classes.
Everything in Java has to be defined within a class.
If you use Java P, Java P, I forget what the P stands for.
But it's saying, like I wanna see run to $1.
This is showing you what the closure class is.
So this is your anonymous class, new runable.
And notice it's getting an int val x, which it got from here.
So that's what the compiler does for you.
So this JavaP will take your bytecode and actually show you like some structure of the
classes that you've created.
And again, it's got this $1 name.
Okay.
So that's nested classes.
And now I will start JavaScript.
The JavaScript is not related to Java, except for marketing purposes.
So at the time that the web was taking off, Sun, the predecessor to Oracle, had two different
languages.
One was the back end language, Java.
And JavaScript was the front end language for the browser.
And for marketing reasons, they both got the name Java in them or the word Java in them.
So you're left with the dot com boom sort of marketing world
that we were living in 20, 30 years ago.
So now, we'll look at JavaScript as a language,
and we will see if we can make sense of it.
I always struggle to make sense of it.
All right.
So basics.
We have numbers, characters, strings,
So there's one C in single quotes.
It's a character, a string literal there.
We have expressions, so 1 plus 2 is an expression.
We have arrays, so this syntax here is an array.
We have undefined not a number and null.
If we want to create an object literal, we can do this.
We can use the braces.
and we can set these are all properties.
We can define functions using the function keyword.
We have side effecting expressions
that result in undefined.
So actually, if I execute this line of code,
this expression, the type of this expression is,
or the thing that it results in is undefined.
Sort of weird.
We do have statements.
So semicolon turns expressions into statements.
So function declarations have to have a return type if you expect it to
be anything other than undefined.
So if we drop the word return here, even though we do this addition,
the function itself will return undefined.
do it. So a lot of the reason for this is because, well, I've heard two things said.
JavaScript has a language goal of letting the most crappy code execute. The other thing
I've heard is that at the time that they were designing the language, they wanted it
to, they thought everybody is going to be writing code for the web. Everybody is going
to be writing code for the web and most people are not going to make great programmers and
And so we're going to end up with a lot of mess.
So we're going to try really hard to have the code run,
no matter what.
And if it doesn't work, well, then the programmer
has to go figure out why.
So instead of having like, JavaScript
is not going to, compiler isn't going
to refuse to execute the code.
It's going to try to execute the code as much as possible.
So we do get built-in support for manipulating the DOM.
So I don't know if you've ever heard of the DOM before, the document object model.
But basically, XML was also all the rage about 26 years ago.
I actually worked at a company that decided we were going to have XML because it was cool.
And we wrote all of our configuration files in XML.
That's all we did.
Working at a financial exchange, you don't.
This is all text, right?
That's like really expensive.
It's a lot of data.
We're talking about this right now.
I'm interfacing with a system at work.
It gives me XML.
it's something called soap. Stay away from soap. Soap is a bad thing. But it
gives me all this XML and we were having a discussion today about well we're
gonna convert it to a JSON model, like a standard modern model, but we're also
going to potentially, later on, need to add fields that we didn't get and oh by
the way we may not be able to go back to the source of the data and get it again
in the future.
So we're going to save everything we ever get
and store it in Google GCP spam.
So this is very verbose.
It's a lot of text.
It's not great for if you're on,
like if you're trying to write a trading system.
We wouldn't do that.
But they decided that since XML was cool,
we needed to use it.
So we wrote our configuration files in XML.
All right.
So JavaScript, because XML was all the rage
and we were communicating information
between browsers and servers using XML,
they decided that JavaScript was going
to have built-in support for manipulating
the document object model.
Also HTML is like a subset of XML.
Right?
And it, yeah.
I don't even know if that's the right thing to say.
but it's very similar.
We also are going to have built-in support
for functional programming, so call back functions
to handle events.
So like events, something happens,
you need to update the UI on the browser.
So we have built-in support for that.
So here's our name function, I guess.
We have statically-stoped mutable variables.
There's global storage.
We have iterators here.
So here we're actually iterating through this array.
And then we're constructing these functions.
Objects have properties, and then you can add event listeners to the document.
It's a very different type of programming than I do,
because I do like back end services.
You don't need these things for backend services.
You need certain language features, but it's a lot less structured than I'm used to.
So, we're dynamically typed.
So here's our function f.
We're gonna log x.
We're gonna log the property data on x and then the length of data on x.
So if we try this with different inputs, if we call f,
with this array.
Look its output well.
x is an object.
So it's going to print that.
So an array ends up being an object.
Then we're going to call x.data.
We're going to print x.data.
So the data is 112131.
So it's going to print that.
And then here the data length is 3.
So then we print that.
But I can also call f on a string.
So we don't have the typing stuff that we're used to.
So here, I'm calling f on it.
And in fact, I'm calling f on this object literal that
contains one property called data.
And here, I'm calling f on a string.
So in my first log statement, I log pizza because the string
That's the object that I got.
My second log statement, I'm trying
to access a property called data on a string.
That doesn't exist, so I get undefined.
And then at O, the plot thickens,
so then I try to dereference the property data, which
is undefined, and then I try to get the length property
on data, which is a type error.
So now we're going to get type errors.
Uncaught type error cannot read property length
of undefined.
So you're going to get all kinds of weirdness that you wouldn't expect coming from statically typed languages.
So once I had to learn JavaScript pretty quick for a job I had, it was a consulting gig,
and luckily, I may have said this to you all before, but luckily a guy I worked with had a pretty strong CS background,
and I had a master's in CS, and I had loved this class, so I knew what questions to ask.
I knew how to think about languages.
Alright, so here's a new function f.
This time we're going to print x divided by 2 in the first log message, and then we're
also going to print the zeroth element of x, if such a thing exists.
So here, when I call f, this time it's not an object, it's just the array, right?
So here, if I try to divide an array by 2, I get not a number.
Real weird.
And if I try to access the 0th element, I get the 0.
Oh, that works as I would expect.
If I try to call this f with my number 8, so this time my first log line will do 8 divided
and I'll get 4, so that'll work.
Then I'm trying to access the zeroth element
of a number, 8, which is not defined.
So the typing is dynamic.
So this is classic dynamic typing.
I'll put on undefined, I could pass undefined.
OK, if I pass undefined and I try to divide that by 2,
I get not a number.
If I try to access the zeroth element of undefined,
I get cannot read property 0 of undefined.
So dynamically typed.
That's what this is.
So object literals.
So we get these weird type conversions
that we might not expect.
So this is an array literal, this is an object literal.
If I take two arrays and I use plus,
I get a string, sorry, an empty string.
If I take an array and an object, I get this thing,
I'm not even sure how to describe that.
And then I guess this is the Visual Studio 8.
So here, if I take an object and add an array,
I get the same thing, object object.
Oh no, sorry, in Visual Studio 8 I get zero,
and in Node.js I get object object.
So this is now gonna depend on the implementation, right?
Here, if I do this, in Visual Studio 8,
I get not a number, and then in, I think that's VSE.
I'm not Visual Studio, I don't know what VSE means.
The point is that there are different interpreters.
So if I'm using node, like on my machine, or in a browser,
I might get something different.
So you're going to get these weird type converters
that you don't expect.
So dynamic types and optional arguments
create surprising results.
So if I have this, well, this is the one that always
throws me I had to look it up again.
So what do we think is going on here?
So this is what I'm trying to teach you,
when you encounter stuff on a language like this,
how do you reason about that?
I have an array of three strings.
They each have one zero, right?
So they're the exact same string.
And this looks like I'm currying.
We saw currying, right?
So I've got parse int and I'm calling map on it
and I get 10, not a number, and two.
Does anybody have any idea why?
I know, I had to look it up.
Does anybody know where?
So there's- this just drove me nuts.
So what I did earlier, I'm gonna do it again.
I'm gonna take this and I'm gonna copy.
And I'm gonna paste it into clod and I'm gonna say-
I'm giving you a little lesson on how to use clod, does it work?
Yes.
I'm going to then say, why?
And it's going to tell me that array.map passes three arguments to its callback.
The element, the index, and the array itself.
Parsint accepts two, a string and a radix.
this because so parsant zero is treated as base 10.
This is treated as base 1, radix one is invalid.
And this is treated as binary, radix 2.
So then, it says to wrap it so the only element, so
only the element is passed.
So you'd have to look, so from here, you would look at the definition of parsant
to see what it's taking.
And then you would also look at the definition of map, right?
So before we had Claude, that's what I would have done.
I would have looked it up.
But I've gotten quite lazy now that Claude's there to help.
However, be careful.
Claude will do all kinds of things.
We're having discussions at work about how
to deal with developers who are less experienced than us,
who are coming up with Claude answers and not telling us.
And we're like, Claude did that.
You didn't do that.
Because you didn't think that through.
Anyway, what I would do from here
is validate them what is coming to me is correct.
but I remember this, there's something to do
with the way parsing is defined.
And something to do with the way array.map is defined.
So you'd have to look.
So that, when I first saw this I was like,
what the heck is this?
So here, if I sort 1, 5, 20, 10, I'm gonna get 1, 10, 25,
and that's because it's actually sorting these,
looks like it's converting them to strings,
And it's sorting them as strings and not numbers.
So you would think that five would show up here,
after the one.
But it's not sorting them as numbers,
it's sorting them as strings.
Oh, and luckily, the slide actually,
I didn't actually click this earlier,
but you can go look at the definition.
It's right here.
So, all right.
Undefined and not a number, infinity.
So you can take undefined and add one and get not a number.
That's real intuitive to me.
You can take false and add one and get one, so somebody liked C because in C, true and
false are 1, 0.
Or true and false are actually non-zero and zero, right, in C. So somebody likes C.
If I take 5 divided by zero, I get infinity.
And if I take minus one divided by zero, I get minus infinity.
OK.
So type conversion and equality.
So there's a lot of details here.
I think the next slide actually.
So these are the answers.
So we'll go through those.
So empty string is equal to a single character string with zero
in it.
False, that seems obvious.
But zero is that equal to empty string.
And if you use double equally, you get true.
If you use that, you get true.
So it's doing some kind of a conversion.
Here, conversion.
Conversion.
10 greater than nine, true.
The string one, zero greater than the string nine, false,
because this occurs before that
if you go alphanumerically, character-wise.
1 plus 9 is 10,
1 plus single character 9, well it'll do string.
It'll convert and then do string concatenation.
.
1 plus single character 9 equals 19, and we'll convert back.
Oh boy.
You know, minus 1 plus 11, well, that'll convert that to a string.
And then this will convert to an int and subtract 1.
So over there we have some other ones for false.
What is false equal to?
Is true bigger than false yes.
Can I divide by zero?
Is five divided by zero equal to six divided by zero?
So because that ends up being infinity.
That's true.
Zero divided by zero is gonna be not a number, not an infinity.
So those are not gonna be the same.
It's confusing.
Floats are awful.
They suck as usual.
So this is precision issues.
Right?
It's going to do stuff with precision issues.
So here's the important point.
Use triple equals, which does know conversions.
So if you're working with JavaScript
and you're getting weirdness, double check.
Now, in Scala, I use triple equals all the time.
I don't think it's in native Scala,
but it's in typoval Scala.
So I use as it's kind of my default.
So now we have a feature called hoisting.
So variables var are going to be function scopes.
So if I have in here, in this block, we have var a,
the definition of a is going to be hoisted to the top of the nearest
closing function.
So this is the function.
And I'm defining a in this block.
Well, a will actually be defined here at line three.
But the initialization code is not going to be hoisted.
So you see in the comments over here,
a is undefined, but it does exist at this line of code.
Now it gets the update.
it gets updated to have the value of two,
and then I have my log this.
And then here, what's going on here?
A equals A.
So that's going to give me this A out here, right?
And then I call F, and here,
I have A equals one here.
So here's the equivalent code, right?
So I think this is just pointing out that the scope is static.
Static scope, yes.
I got confused, because of all the dynamic stuff going on.
I was like, wait, that's gotta be static scope based on the way it's behaving.
But yeah, that confirms it.
So all it's really done is pull the definition over there.
So then, and
And I don't know, I don't remember what ES6 stands for.
It's something to do with JavaScript land.
It was some revision to the language.
Do you know Matt?
I don't know if you do stuff with the time.
No, I hate JavaScript.
Okay, you hate JavaScript, okay.
You're in good companies.
So yeah, it introduced this block oriented scope.
So they added these things, let and const,
And so that will make it so that A,
this A is not defined until here,
so the A out here is gonna be the one
that we got from there,
because we used let and the same thing with const.
So, let is mutable and const is immune.
Hoisting a var to the top of the function
will happen everywhere.
So here's my main.
So I call f with true.
I have a defined.
I call f of true.
I'm just going to change a here to be two.
And then if true, then I have a new var a.
Well this var got hoisted up here,
so the a I changed was this one.
And then I increment that A.
Let's see.
Yeah, so this will make the declaration here, so the A I update is 2, so then on console
log it, it should get, oh, I got three.
Why'd I get, oh because A plus 1, thanks.
so that this executed, right?
So I got a plus 1, so that a is now 3.
And then I exit out and then m1.
a is back to being 1 because it's this one.
And then if I call a, if I call, what is it, f of false,
I'll never execute this.
And so I won't hoist probably.
I think that's the point of this, right?
It's still hoist.
Oh, it's still hoist?
Yeah, you're right, because it's defined.
It had to parse the whole thing before it could even execute it.
So we don't change it.
So we just set it equal to two.
And then we exit out, and we get, oh wait, before we exit out,
we get F, A is two, that's right.
And then I exit out.
And because of hoisting, my A is in scope for the entire function.
And so the A that I have out here is still one.
Thank you.
So making sense of this language is a joy.
So the hoisting happens even when the variable is already
used above the bar declaration.
In JavaScript, we have functional programming.
So functions and objects are first-class citizens.
We can create them at runtime.
We can pass them as arguments.
We can return them.
We can store them in data structures.
nested functions and objects are commonplace
for callbacks collections process.
JavaScript uses statical lexical scoping
and there's this link to see here.
Let's see what he wants.
Oh, this talks about closures in JavaScript.
So you can take a look at that.
So it does have to use closures of course,
because whenever you have functional programming
and you have an environment,
you have free variables,
environments that need to define the meaning for those free variables so you have to have those.
So JavaScript, the standard includes tail call optimization, but only Safari implements it,
at least as of the time that these slides were.
It can still make sense to think about alternative implementation. So here,
So I think the point of this is even though you're only going to get tail call optimization
in safari, it still makes sense to implement a function like Fibonacci this way because
you might luck out and execute on something that does support them.
So argument passing and pattern matching.
So we are going to use call by value,
but objects and arrays will be references.
That's similar to the way it works in Java.
It's actually call by value in Java, like I said,
but effectively, you're dealing with references
to memory here.
So here, objects and arrays are going to be references.
And if you change fields or elements,
then you'll see that outside the code that you called.
you'll see it from the column code.
There is a pattern match functionality for arrays.
So if you have an array, if A happens to be an array,
and you have this here, you'll deconstruct that array.
And then you can swap, like that.
If I swap an array with more, so in this function
that I've defined, I'm only swapping the first two elements.
If I do this, then I'll swap these two,
but I'll leave the 3 and 4 there.
I can swap in place.
So here, I can let x equal 1, and y equal 2.
Here, I've created an array with 1, 2.
And now, I'm swapping, because I'm referring to I'm binding
to y and x, so 1 is bound to x, and 2 is bound to y.
And now, I'm just switching over.
So that syntax works.
This stuff's a little weird.
I didn't have time to actually play with it myself.
So what this is doing, I think, is I have person.
This is an object with some properties.
And I'm binding the name, and this one
is binding the age to nothing.
And then we're binding the address.
But I think I can do, it might make sense to actually do this.
Let's get out of here and type new.
So there's again, because I did this assignment, I got undefined.
why I printed under Thighnair. So if I then do this.
The underscore doesn't make sense, I think.
I'm sorry? The underscore doesn't make sense.
Yeah, you know what? I mean, you may be right, but I've remembered now that
whenever I do this stuff, it doesn't behave exactly the way I expect because
I'm used to the Scala REPL and you can overwrite things.
So let's try that again.
I'm going to do that one.
You're saying the underscore doesn't make sense.
So here, name got Alice, ADDR address got that,
And then the underscore is just like a wildcard, right?
It doesn't do anything.
It's just, yeah.
So it's just saying like if there's a property after name
but before a address, just ignore it.
But then the reason I had to exit out,
so if I do this,
then do this again.
I'm going to copy paste.
And now I'm going to do this line and I should get,
will it bind name correctly?
Yeah, it did, yeah it did that.
And then this stuff, when I started to see this,
I was like I'm not sure.
So let's get a fresh one.
Get this.
And then I'll do this last line.
I'm not sure what the underscore 1 and 2 do.
So n is undefined.
I'm not sure why.
Underscore 1 is undefined.
Because it probably couldn't match.
It doesn't know how to match anything.
So it doesn't make sense.
We'll take a break now and we'll come back to continuing laboring through this and doing
fire .
We're almost done with this set of slides, but I want to take a break and pick it up.
You can come back at 35 after.
I was just able to use a machine to make sure it's safe.
I'm going to use this for the last two months.
I want to use the small one of my favorite parts of the world.
I will have a few more times.
I also want to use the other parts to help me.
I want to use the other parts of my own.
It's been very nice to have a lot of fun.
I'm going to use the other parts of my own.
so
...
We are going to be using a simple tool.
I'll use a mobile phone to use a smartphone.
I'll use a mobile phone.
And we'll do the same thing.
I can't believe this.
Next, we can set your way to the top.
This is the first time you choose to use.
I like to use a simple cookie pan-tap.
I like to use a simple cookie pan.
This is a simple cookie pan.
I like to use a cookie pan-tap.
You can use a cookie pan-tap.
Dish.
Thank you.
OK.
so
I added it in the water.
I had to put the coffee in the water.
I added the water.
It is delicious.
The water is very good.
I don't think it's a good idea.
I like to make it easier.
I don't know.
I'm hungry, I'm hungry.
I can't eat it, but I'm hungry.
Alright.
I love it.
Thank you.
And then I'll turn the bell to the bell.
So, I'll try to save this.
The end of the day is that the end of the day is the end of the day.
The end of the day is not too close to the day.
The end of the day is that the end of the day is too close to the day.
Now, the end of day is the end of the day.
In this case, I'm going to go to the bottom of the bottom.
We'll have a small size.
We can use this one.
So, we have to use the bottom of the bottom.
We will use this one to make sure we can remove.
So, I think it's good to be a good one.
I don't know.
I think it's good to be a good one.
So, I'm going to try it.
And as I said, I'm going to try it.
Because I'm going to try it.
So, I'm going to try it.
So, it's quick.
I'm going to do it.
so
...
So let's get started.
I've got a nice dressing room for a couple of hours and I've got a nice dressing room for a long time.
I'm going to put some dressing room in the room and make it a little extra fit.
I'm going to put the dressing room in the room so that I can be used in the room for a long time.
I'm going to go ahead and get started.
I'll get it.
Let me still want our thoughts.
We must be doing presentations or something.
So...
Oh, wow.
All right, let's pick up our tour of JavaScript.
So language has built into it map, filter, and fold in modern JavaScript.
So when it originally came out of course we weren't really doing these things generally speaking.
They existed in certain functional languages.
What JavaScript came out of wasn't the people working with it
weren't thinking that way yet.
So you can do lambda expressions.
So here we have our array 11, 21, 31.
And we're mapping.
So we should, I think we should.
Can we get the answers?
Does it actually print?
No, it doesn't.
So I think if we were to try that code there, all of these,
and we put that in node.
I'm going to start a new one just to be clear.
So for this one, this ended up, oh,
this is undefined because it's just an assignment statement.
Here we're mapping sort of multiplying by 2 so we get 22, 42 and 62.
Here we're filtering and we're keeping only those that satisfy this predicate of
being divisible by 7.
Notice we're using triple equal there just to be sure that we're not getting a strange conversion.
And then here we're reducing so this is actually going to do a sum, right?
So if you add those up you get 63, right?
So, we aren't just showing you lambda expressions.
You can also do this with functions.
So, you can actually define a function here.
Like in line there like that.
The return keyword is required.
Because otherwise, if you don't use return,
you will get, I think, undefined.
And then the outer this is not closed.
I know what outer this not closed means, I'm sort of like why is that there.
So the return is mandatory.
And I guess the beware is these are two separate things to be aware of.
So the return is mandatory and then if you're trying to refer to
something in s, it's not going to be closed.
So remember in Java,
we have to have this effectively final i from enclosing scope.
So here's my i.
Sorry. Yeah, well,
we have to make i effectively final by aliasing it like this.
So this is accepted in Java.
If I do this in JavaScript,
I can share the i and I get the unwanted effect with var.
So here my var got hoisted, right?
So because it got hoisted, f i is defined as part of this function.
Then if it's not in a function,
I guess it would be in the browser context or in the global context.
So the closure is gonna store a reference to the shared mutable variable i.
And that's actually important, so that I ends up being shared
across all the different functions
that we construct in there.
So can we fix it with a VAR similar to Java?
And again, hoisting, right?
So we should use block scoped let or const.
So that will make it so we don't get hoisting.
You can also use the let directly in the for and get the same results.
So if you do that, it scopes the i to each value by each iteration of the..
I'm sorry, each execution of the loop by its its own i.
So that's the end of our basic tour.
I didn't know how long it was going to take
to get through four slides, so I was like,
well, let's just do break now, and come back, so.
JavaScript is standardized as ECMAScript.
I don't know much about these.
New editions are released regularly.
So there's the specification.
You can read up on it.
So this is I guess 2019 version.
I don't know if there's a later version.
As a non-JavaScript programmer, I don't care,
and it doesn't matter.
You don't need to know that.
The best documentation is going to come from Mozilla.
Yeah, this is Mozilla, developer.mozilla.org,
so you're going to get the best documentation from there.
And this is interesting, so the compatibility.
So this shows you the different implementations of Javascript, right?
They're implement...
So along the top here we have these different implementations and it's a pretty big list.
I'm trying to see...
I don't get a scroll bar at the bottom.
It's sort of strange because this sort of goes on.
Somewhere there's the one about...
What is the Tailcall Optimization?
Notice it's red across,
and then it starts turning green.
I'm gonna put this in.
This is that funky browser that's running through WSL,
so I'm gonna put it open here.
Normally when I have these slides, yeah.
There we go.
I don't know.
It's so strange that I don't have the scroll bar.
Anyway.
Sorry.
I'll have to try Firefox.
I think I do.
Whenever I get behavior I don't like, I'm always like, well, let's just try it.
trying to do it.
There we go.
That's what I wanted.
We'll just use it here.
So, tell call optimization.
Yeah. So you'll see that one is not implemented anywhere except it's in Safari.
Oh that's why I guess. Because that's... Safari 18. Anyway. These are all the features of
the language on the left. And then these are all of the implementations, the browsers,
Firefox, Chrome, Edge, Safari. And this just shows you where things are...
compatible. I'm not even sure what the numbers are in here.
But if you're going to do anything substantial in JavaScript, you probably will end up
needing to be aware of these things.
Let's go back to this one.
So the bad parts were eventually fixed.
Oh, somebody's blog post from 10 years ago, OK?
Bad parts, so.
I'm not sure what the bad parts are.
Here's some book recommendations if you end up
needing to do stuff with JavaScript,
you don't know JS.
Which is funny.
And then Axel Rauschmiers ExploringJS.
So that's the basic introduction to JavaScript and its weirdness in my considered opinion.
And now we'll talk about something in JavaScript that is related to what we've been talking about with object orientation.
But instead of having this where we define classes and having this idea of static relationships between class definitions,
In JavaScript, we're going to have something that's delegation-based, and we'll talk about
what that means.
So does object-oriented programming require classes and inheritance?
So we'll talk about this thing called delegation-based OOP in JavaScript, and we'll talk about delegation
chains.
So remember, JavaScript object literals.
These things are created by using these curly braces and they're syntactic primitives.
You can actually have a class declaration that are not syntactic primitives.
I think the difference there is that JavaScript is actually taking your class and converting
it to something that could be represented in that.
Delegation is going to end up replacing class-based inheritance.
So before in Java and Scala and C++, we have this static notion of relationships between
types if you're extending.
And in JavaScript we don't.
So remember that objects have properties, so if I have an empty object, I can declare
an empty object and call it empty, like that.
I can have my person with name, age, and address.
It has three properties.
I can access my properties like this.
I can update my properties.
So I can change things like that.
I can access an undefined property.
So on my person here, there is no occupation property.
So if I try to do that, I get undefined.
And then if I try to access the undefined property,
or the property that was not defined,
I get an uncaught type error.
It cannot read property length.
So an object is basically just a map from string to value.
So when you have that, oh it's right there.
So I have keys, name, age, and address,
and for each of these keys, name has the value Alice,
the key age has the value 50,
The key adder has the value of 243 south Labech Abbey.
So we can use this dot notation when the string has no spaces.
But if you have, oh, if I wanna, sorry, if I wanna,
what this is saying is there's a way, it's not illustrating it next, but
this string in the name might actually have a space in the name.
So that's why that's there.
If I want to add a property occupation,
I can just do that on the fly.
I can just say person.occupation now has developer.
If I want to add a property called happyPlace,
I can't use the dot notation.
I have to use this because the space in here.
So if I want to list all the properties,
then I go like this for P in person.
I can actually just, and this will actually bind P for each iteration of the loop, it'll
bind P to the next property.
There's some notion of order.
So it'll do name Alice, age, 50, address, 243 South, occupation, developer, happy place,
home.
If I want to turn an object into a JSON string, I can just call JSON.stringify on that object
And it will convert it into this thing.
Remember, JSON is JavaScript object notation.
And basically, this is a way for us to.
So this is actually how most of the world does data
transfer over the internet now.
And we don't use XML like they were 20-something years ago.
They're using this now.
Functions can be named or anonymous.
So here I have objects with number property n and function property get.
So counter one dot get will give me zero.
And counter two dot get will give me zero.
And when it does the get, it's actually doing an increment on n.
I can actually access the function so I can actually in an array just construct an array
where each of the object is the get function on each of the respective objects.
Functions are values of properties, not methods.
So we don't have methods like we have in static languages.
So we have this.
This is mandatory to access other properties of an object.
So you have to use this.
If you try to do this here without the word this, it won't work.
You'll get some kind of undefined.
So if I increment counter 1, that'll work.
If I increment counter 2, I'll get an uncaught reference
error, and it's not defined in the object yet.
So I didn't say this, so it doesn't know that I'm looking there.
So all properties are public.
So this is that thing in some of the languages we've been using where you can declare things
to be private or protected.
In JavaScript, all properties end up being public.
So if I want to increment counter1, I can actually change counter1.n to 30.
And then call get, and it will return 30, but it will also have increment into 31.
I can emulate encapsulation by using closures.
So here, I'm gonna create an array of counters.
L value, which is this thing here, uses array notation.
I'm sorry, this whole thing here is the L value.
It's the left to this side.
Uses the array notation to decompose into elements.
So here, I call createCounter, I'll createCounter again.
And that will give me this function here.
It will return this, sorry,
this ob, sorry, it'll give me this object that has a get function here.
So it returns an object literal with closure for a function get.
c1 and c2 each have their own end, so they were, when create counter was called there
was a new end created for each one of those.
If I try to increment c1, that works.
If I try to increment both c1 and c2, so here I'm just taking c1 and c2 and
putting them in an array and then calling map where I call the get function on
their respective objects.
would get 1 for C1 because I already do this here and then 0
here.
Closure variables are not fields.
So what does this mean?
Well, if I have this code here, so I call createCounter,
I'm returning this object which is delineated by these braces
here and then I have this get function in my object.
I call c1.get, so I'm going to call this get that I got, this.n will be undefined.
Because there's no n defined outside of here.
Here I have n equals, I'm printing out n equals 0.
So here, because it doesn't have this, it's looking for a property, and for some reason it's deciding that that's equal to zero.
I don't know how JavaScript works, honestly.
And then here it's doing this dot n plus plus.
So since this dot n is undefined.
Oh, sorry.
I get it.
This n comes from here.
So when I say this n.
The n referenced here is declared here inside createCounter and got passed in the closure.
There's so many things going on that my brain lost it.
So the point here is that if I try this dot n, there's no this context that I can get my n meaning from.
This would be more of the line where I go, I don't understand why they design this.
But that is this way, but that is how it works.
So that's why this prints out undefined here.
and then this one prints out zero because this one was zero here.
And then the, what's the last thing?
So not a number from undefined plus plus, right?
So here when I try to access this dot n again, I got undefined, right?
And then I'm trying to increment but that's, if I take undefined from the previous set of slides,
if I take undefined and try to increment, I get not a number.
Oh, this is a good point to stop and just say, the study guide has basically all the
– and the quiz for next week and the homework have all the practice you really need.
So, like, don't worry about memorizing all of this crazy random behavior that's happening.
The homework, the quiz, and the study guide questions will reinforce the things you need
to study.
So hopefully that helps, don't freak out about all these things because I don't
even remember all the details. So what is this if there is no class? So this is what
I was starting to say before, JavaScript binds this based on the calling context.
So I guess I misspoke before, we do have methods. If I do o.m, that's method
to context, so this would be O. F is function to context, so this would be the global window.
And then if I'm in a constructor context where I'm constructing a new object of C that I
created, this is that new object. So this is documented in the Mozilla docs.
So method context here, so in my bar o, I have an object with a get this which returns
this.
If I call o.getThis, is it equal to o?
Yes, that's true.
In a function context, so if I have bar f this is o.getThis, so basically getting a reference
to the function here and then I call FBIS and get O back.
I'm sorry, I'm asking do I get O back?
That's false.
This is not going to be closed in this context.
And then you get some different behavior.
If it's node.js, this is going to be global context.
That's like I'm doing on the machine where I type node
and I put something.
If I'm in a browser, I'm going to get the context
This will be the window.
So JavaScript methods are properties that hold functions.
In JavaScript, this is not bound in the closure.
So if we have a closure that's happening, that's being created,
this ends up not being bound.
So in here, I have f next is going to be o.next.
And so when I call that, this is not bound.
In Scala, methods are not functions.
Oh, yeah.
So this is interesting.
There is a blog post.
Oh, my Tim, okay.
Oh, okay.
He's written a lot of things that I, a lot of code that I use.
Never met the person.
Methods are not functions in Scala.
and then he wrote a big, long blog post that I should probably read.
But in Scala, this ends up being closed when converting the method to a function.
So here in Scala, if I have object O, you know, bar n, and I have a def next,
and then I say, oh, I want my f next to refer to O dot next,
and it's using this syntax here to mean that I want this to convert this method to a function,
and then I call that function, the closure will still bind like before.
So this will be slightly different in JavaScript.
So what is wrong below?
So, so what do we have here, so we have o which is our object.
We're calling add on it and passing this array, 10, 20, 30, and
I'm mapping over that array.
At the function, oh return this.v plus x.
So this.v is going to end up being undefined,
and then when we add x to it, we get another number.
So inside the map function is,
inside map is function context.
So this refers to the global window.
So this just refers to your global scope, your global variable score.
And since v isn't defined in the global variable score, it has a meaning.
V is defined here in my o.
It's a property of o.
So I guess before ES5 fix, there was, you would have to do this to alias.
You have to do this to alias this.
So you have to declare a bar me equals this, and now you've copied it.
You're outside the map, but inside add is method context, so this refers to up.
Unlike this, the ordinary variable me is closed.
So this doesn't get closed because me is an ordinary variable and
it's part of this function context.
I mean, it would be hoisted if it were declared lower because it's var,
but it's in scope for this whole function.
So that's closed, it passed in the close.
So manual binding, this is the fix.
I guess, what this is doing is saying, this dot v,
so it must be getting the v there.
Oh, manual binding.
It's calling dot bind.
Oh boy.
Ugh.
Even more crazy weird.
So in ES6, we can use Lambda notation, and that will work.
So in this one, we're explicitly
binding this in the math function context to this in add method
.
In JavaScript, lambda expressions are not ordinary functions.
So a lambda expression is not an ordinary function like that.
Unlike functions, this is closed in lambda expressions.
So it can get really confusing to remember all of this.
Yeah, that face you're making, Matt,
is like when I first had to do anything in JavaScript.
These people should be in prison.
Yeah, I know.
It's like the inmates are running the asylum
or something like that.
So yeah, so creating an object with a function.
So function builds and returns an object literal.
So this function is going to construct
this object, which will have n and another property.
So n is one property with minus 1,
and next is another property which has this function.
So if I call createCounter, I'm in function context in here.
And then c2 createCounter, and then c1.next, c2.next,
it will, each one of the, oh sorry, c1.next, c1.next, c1,
2.next, and then c1.next.
They will have their own n.
That's what this is showing.
So c1.next, we'll do that increment.
So we will increment 0.
It will return 0 and increment after the return.
And then it will do it again.
So that'll give us 1.
And then it'll do it again over here.
And that'll give us 2 in this position.
But this one is pointing to a different one.
So that one is going to give us 0 back and increment
the other end 1.
So if I call a function using new, then I get constructor context.
What does that mean?
Well, that will actually construct an object with the new counter.
So it's going to construct an object with these things.
And then, right, so now I have these objects, C1 and C2.
and then I call those.
So it binds this to the newly created object
inside the function.
So like this will actually create this object
with an N property and a next property,
which is a function.
So this starts to show you
the picture of what's going on here.
So there's this thing called proto,
which is analogous to like your super type in a statically type language.
So in this case, I have a function counter and it's prototype,
meaning it's what we would say in static languages, it's super class.
Although it's not the right word in the area of language theory.
It inherits from this function that it's pointing to through this proto link.
That's property.
C1 is an object that has an N and
it has a next function which gets its next function from over here.
This starts to confuse me.
But this is starting to show you like the way these relationships end up being structured.
So if I do R cx is counter, I didn't say new, so I'm in function context,
not constructor context.
So I get cx.next.
That's going to be an uncaught error because cx ends up being undefined.
There was no return in my function counter, so the thing returned undefined.
So using that other rule from before.
Yes, these people should be impressed.
What if you return this from Counter?
I don't know.
You want to try?
I would encourage you to try things out when you have questions like that.
I would do both try it out yourself and maybe ask Claude and try it out yourself and see
if Claude agrees or whatever.
I don't know.
It probably would return whatever the function.
So if you said return, what did you ask?
Like what if you return this from the .
This?
Yeah, since they're using this dot end,
use native one, is that gonna be something illegal
or is there gonna be some other weird thing
that they're like, yeah, you can do that, I guess,
I mean, you mean my interest now,
I'm gonna have to try it, right?
Let's try it.
All right, so here's that.
Then we had.
What I would say, if you return this
from that as the last line in that function.
I know. First, I just want to see I'm not doing that yet so first I'm just doing
what's on the slide right so then I'm gonna do this and I should get
0102, and then because that's new, we're really over here, right?
So let's redo this, but let's have it return this.
Is that what you're saying?
Yeah.
I'm going to restart this.
Okay.
Did I plug?
So, before we hit enter, we will add the line return this, right?
Oh, let me do that.
Fine.
Return.
Well let me overwrite this.
Okay.
You know what?
I'm sorry, we've got to do that again, because I do not trust.
Paste, but I won't hit enter, I will now say return this.
This is what you were saying, right?
Yeah.
Like that.
And then over here, we're in function context.
So we want to know what happens.
And that's just undefined because we did an assignment, right?
But then the question is CX dot X, right?
That worked.
Yeah, that worked.
Would you type window dot next, so if it's not in function context then does it not
bind the window now?
Yeah, it doesn't work.
Uncaught reference error.
It's messing with your bind.
We should use global because it's Node context.
Oh yeah, that's a good point.
What's global?
Is that for-
There's syntax.
You mean the syntax, right?
There's global something.
Yeah.
It's just when you don't have the window-
Oh, global.next.
Next to next, yes.
Oh, I see what you're saying.
Because this is node.
Duh.
Yeah, it worked.
Yeah.
All right, so you get both if you return this.
Say again?
So you get both if you return this from the function.
Yeah.
Cool.
Good.
Isn't it?
Every object has its own set of methods.
c1.next is not going to be the same as c2.next.
Okay, sharing property.
So JavaScript functions are objects and so then, therefore, they can have properties.
So I can define properties on prototype object of function.
Names are looked up along delegation chain proto.
That was what I was starting to show you on that last thing.
So here, encounter, I have this.end is going to get minus one.
And then my prototype.next is going to be this other function.
So do we start to see a picture?
Yeah, so what we have is counter prototype next is going to be equal to this function here,
which does this return plus plus this dot n.
And it has a prototype of function,
because you're dividing a function,
so you get prototype function.
But then you change counter's prototype to be this.
There's proto and prototype.
It gets confusing.
So C1 and C2 in this code here we call
this is constructor context, we call new.
And C1 and C2 share counter.prototype.
C1.next is equal to C2.
triple equals C2.next.
So they will be the same because of where they were defined.
And when it goes to look up a function,
so when you're calling a function,
JavaScript will look in the object,
and if it doesn't find it, it looks in the prototype,
which is the equivalent of looking in the super type
in our statically typed world.
So delegation-based inheritance.
So we have a delegation chain with this proto thing.
So all objects end up having proto properties.
And each object's proto property is
going to point to another object.
So it will resolve names by searching proto recursively
until found.
I'm not sure why these links are here.
That's probably where it's defined.
And maybe these are new because last quarter of these
weren't here, so I get these from.
So this just shows you the documentation for inheritance in the prototype chain.
That's the one.
Oh, you know what this is probably just three different places that it's documented.
Or, well, this is probably somebody's blog post, okay.
Interesting.
And then JavaScript, this might be...
So that's a hacker noon, talking about it.
And then on the right here...
So the point of this is that every object has this proto thing, which is the equivalent
of its supertype, and you can dynamically change that because it's just a big old linked list.
Proto is like your Next, but it's just going off in the delegation chain.
Then function companion has a prototype.
Only functions have prototype.
So if you see the word prototype, and that's referring to where a function inherits from,
in a constructor context, new objects, this is double underscore proto double underscore.
I'm just gonna call it proto and prototype, alright?
So proto is set to the function's prototype.
And that shows you.
I wouldn't worry about memorizing this.
Again, start to just when you do the homework in the quiz and the study guide, and
we will go over all of the homework,
but the quiz and the study guide will go over.
But come with questions if you have homework questions.
Alright, so we can dynamically update methods at runtime.
If I have this counter here and I...
Let's see, what am I doing?
I'm saying that my prototype next function is that,
And now I can change the behavior of next, dynamically,
static languages are my favorite.
So I can change counters prototype's next function to be that.
And get different behavior so actually in that example.
Here we just called next so we start at minus one,
increment and return. So we get 0, 1, and 2 and now we change this to add 2 each time
and then we call it 3 more times so we get 4, 6, and 8.
We can dynamically change, so before we were changing the method we can update effectively,
some wrong words, but we can effectively update what the Super Class is even though we can't
and we wouldn't use those words.
But this is effectively doing, if you think about it,
you have changing the delegation.
So you have your function up counter,
and then you set the prototype next to do this increment thing.
And it will make that up counter have a next.
And then my down counter, I'm changing the prototype here
to decrement.
And here, I can now, what I'm doing here
is I have C as my up counter.
And I define down counter.
And now what I'm saying is I'm going
to change the behavior by inheriting from a different place.
inheriting again in quotes, because we don't really
use that word for this.
So I'm taking the Downcounter prototype
and making it my prototype for C. So when I call c dot,
next I get decremented.
So here, I'm going to create an object.
So here I have a new printer.
And if I try to call this reset here, that doesn't exist.
I'll get a type error, c.reset is undefined.
So I'll extend the delegation chain here by defining resettable over here.
Now I have a reset function that I've made in my prototype here.
And if I change counters prototype dot proto to resetables prototype,
then I can get this behavior.
And there's a picture.
You can look at that and see what all the things are pointing to.
My eyes start popping out, especially at 8.15 at night.
So here I can create delegation chains.
So here I'm setting resettables prototype proto to object prototype.
So over here we have a picture of what's happening.
And here we have, here we're setting resettables prototype.
Oh, this might be the slide that was broken last quarter.
I think we fixed it because I caught it.
I think this is correct now.
I'm setting counters prototype to be be settable.
So, let me get to the summary.
Don't try to memorize all that.
Just focus on studying what's in the material
I'm giving you to work on for the week.
Object literals are syntactic elements of JavaScript.
Delegation-based OOP.
So essentially, we have this linked list of things.
Instead of inheriting from a class
and having something statically defined,
we have this linked list of where I get responsibility
or where I get references to things from.
So instead of inheriting, like we do in static languages,
we follow this linked list and figure out
what we're referring to.
But we get java-like class syntax that
helps us to set up these delegation sheets.
And that is the end of that.
All right.
So we have about 40 minutes left.
so I would like to turn back to the study guide.
It's not fair.
Does anybody have anything specific from the study guide
that they wanted to go through?
If not, I'm just gonna pick questions
and we're gonna do them.
Spring, study guide.
So I wanted to do 6 last week.
And I think that was the one that we didn't get to,
because I went back.
So why don't we go to 6, start with that one.
And next week, we will definitely do all the ones
from JavaScript, for sure.
And probably the formal symmetrics ones, just to make sure.
And then I'll check the midterm results
and see if there's anything that is most compelling
that we should cover.
Alright, so number six.
Okay, so call by name. So back to our statically-typed world of comfort.
So call by name in Scala delays evaluation of arguments.
So that's that thing we call the thuck, right?
And we request non-strict argument evaluation,
so that means that basically have these expressions
that we don't evaluate.
We implement this in Scala by passing parameter-less
functions as arguments these by convention can be called in Scala even
when omitting the parents resulting code looks as if we were accessing
constricted that's a lot of introductory stuff so let's look at the question so
we have Scala definition our function f takes two funks we have an X that
x that produces an int and a y that produces an int.
But it remains unevaluated, right?
And we return an int in the end.
And then here we say, well, if math.random is less than five,
then we return x, and otherwise we return y.
So we're basically saying like we have a 50-50 chance of returning x or y.
So what is the result of evaluating this expression?
So, F, the first expression is this block of code which remains unevaluated.
And the second expression is this block of code, which remains unevaluated.
So, if we evaluate the whole expression F, when I say remains unevaluated,
I mean this block here doesn't actually execute until it's called for in the function.
So, what happens?
So I'm calling f and I'm passing these two things.
So I'm going to randomly generate something and
then I'm going to evaluate one or the other of these.
And it will actually print something.
So first choice, principal x and y and
returns either one or two, is that true?
Is a possible?
Anybody?
No.
Okay, that's a good guess.
Maybe it's not a guess, maybe you know, and you're just processing.
So why did we say no?
This is not evaluating them until it gets to that line.
random is less than five y never gets reached and so therefore never gets evaluated.
Right. So it's not five is 0.5 but,
what happens is we call this,
we randomly generate some number.
And then we check is it less than 0.5 and if so,
we evaluate x.
And we evaluate x.
That means that we print line x and then we return 1
from this block of code.
But notice we never evaluated y, so we never did that.
There.
OK.
So the answer choice A cannot be true,
because it's not going to print both x and y.
All right.
The expression fails static type checking
because the compound expression does not return int.
Is that true?
Does that compound expression return int?
Does it not turn an int?
What does this compound expression return?
Well, it should return one.
Should return one.
There are lots of different kinds of one.
It's an int one, or a double one, OK.
Right.
But what's the point here?
So it's actually the type of this whole expression between the curly braces is what?
How do we, like how do we know when we look at a compound expression what the type of
that expression is?
Is it the first expression?
Second.
It's the last.
The last one.
It's not the second one.
last one. You could have a thousand things here and the last one is the type
of the entire expression. So to say this thing at choice B, so the
expression fails static type checking because the compound expression does not
return an int. That's false. That is returning an int because that's the last
expression. Okay so well the next choice
Always print y and then return either one or two.
Is that possible?
Nope.
Why?
Because we only print y if we're executing this expression.
If we're executing expression that gets bound to this variable y here.
We either print x and return one or print y and return two.
What do we think about that one?
Sounds plausible, right?
Okay.
I'm going to stick with D.
Letter E says prints X and returns either 1 or 2.
That's the opposite of C, really.
So the answer is D.
And so this is,
be sure you understand what's going on in this code, right?
So this X, because of this syntax here,
this means that this is a thunk.
It's an expression.
The expression remains unevaluated.
until the function needs it.
Actually, if the function
were to refer to it multiple times,
it would actually evaluate it every time.
If I had more code here
that had something else going on
to access x again,
then maybe I would be printing x as well,
like more than once.
The answer is D.
Then let's look at the solution strategy.
So check whether a function argument uses thunk notations.
That's called by name.
In these, sorry, these, I saw the word int, my eye tripped.
These arguments are evaluated non-strict
only when accessed in the function model.
So here's some variations.
We can change the definition here to the definition x and y.
What happens if we change that syntax to that?
When does the first argument get evaluated?
When does the second argument get evaluated?
It gets evaluated when being passed to the function call.
Right.
So, what would get in the question above, what would get printed?
The both lines.
Both X and Y we get printed. So what would happen is, when we call a function, we evaluate the first expression which will execute that whole thing in the curly braces, which means it will do the printing, and then the whole thing evaluates to one, and then one gets passed in to X.
And then the same thing happens for Y. So Y gets printed. And then 2 gets passed in for Y.
And then this code would execute the body of the function would execute the same way.
And it would still only return one or the other, right? But it would have printed both X and Y.
So the difference here is that we've changed this from call by name to call by what?
So that's called by valiant, right?
It's important to recognize that.
If we change the body of F so that instead of this if-then-else thing,
we just did X times Y, but we retain the call by name,
in that case, we would print which or both.
both
and
we would evaluate the variable
x
we would evaluate the expression x
and we would
as a result of executing that code
we would get one
and then we would evaluate y
because we're
referring to them both
we're needing them both
so we'd evaluate the y
print y
So we return two and we would print both in that case.
All right.
So that was six.
Should we do something from last week or
should we do something from earlier?
We can get a two back.
earlier. We can last week? All right, let's do last week. So from last week, the next
one is, let's do number nine. Oh, this isn't... Oh, that's exercise eight. We'll do that
next week. Exercise nine. I was like, no, I'm not doing any more JavaScript tonight.
So, all right, in object-oriented programming,
polymorphism, so this is many forms, polymorphism.
It allows us to refer to an object of a subclass
for a reference that aesthetically type as a face class.
We talked about this a lot at the beginning.
That's upcasting.
We can use this to create generic containers,
but that puts the burden of reading and writing
consistently on programmers.
So what does that mean?
Well, that just means that we can
I don't know what that means.
It seems like it's saying we can have subclasses and then static types.
And then I'm not going to try to parse that type parameters.
Add static type information to container classes that allow the compiler to
check and read, sorry, check, read and write operations for
compatibility with containers.
So, yeah, so we have, in our Scala class,
we have class A with a two string.
We have class B extending A with its own overridden two string.
And class C extending B with its own overridden two string.
And now we have.
The following method uses the classes in containers.
So if I have an array of As, and
And I've constructed new A's.
And I've tried to change this to new C.
And so this is the zero element, and the first element to new A.
And then I call AS.mix string with a comma,
which of the following statements is true.
Does this compile?
Ah, so b extends a and c extends b.
So I have an array of A's, and I set the zeroth element to a new C.
Would that work?
Something is looking weird to me.
So I know what the answer is according to my answer key,
but I'm not sure I agree with it, so now,
I'm going to now do this, let's put this in REPL.
There's something here, I'm missing.
Alright, so we have a, b, and c.
Okay, so here's our, oh, this is the part where I hate, because I have to get these stupid numbers, line numbers.
I have to go back, and I have to delete all the line numbers.
OK, so the answer that I have is wrong.
I was like, the answer key is telling me this is the answer.
And I don't agree with that.
OK, so maybe I wrote it that wrong.
That's possible too.
I have the answer key like on a computer.
I'll have to double check it.
But so we're not going to fail static type checking, right?
We just saw that.
We just saw that it worked.
So we're left with this, I guess.
So it passes that.
And what does it print?
So I think it should print C and A.
because of dynamic dispatch, right?
What do we get?
Oh, I have to run it, okay?
CNA, alright.
So I wonder what happened
and how I got the wrong answer there, that's weird.
I need to check that.
What is that, nine?
Yes.
Oh, no, in my mind, this is what happens
like when you've done JavaScript when you don't want to.
The answer is B on the answer key.
I was like, why is the answer key telling me D?
I was looking at the wrong line.
Okay, so the answer is B, so that is correct.
I was like, how can that be?
So as everybody understand, right,
so it's totally valid to construct a C
and store it in a reference in this array.
This array is an array of As,
and every B is an A, right,
And every C is a B, and it's also an A, because of the hierarchy, right?
So it is perfectly fine to stick a C here, right?
And even though before we had A and A, we can now overwrite the zeroth element with a new C,
and we're overwriting the first element with a new A.
And then we're calling F.
When we call f, this makeString, what this does is it actually goes through the array,
iterates through the array, and it calls toString on each of the elements.
And so it gets back what A, B, or C depending on which one it is.
So in our case we have C and A, right?
And it gets those strings back.
And then it calls makeString, which then concatenates all these strings together
using this separator character in between.
that's why we had C and A. What happens if I change?
Let's jump down to the variations.
If I change array A to array B, so if I change this code here to array B,
would that work?
No.
That's correct.
Why not?
Why do you think that?
Because, what we went over earlier, while B can be where A is,
A cannot be where B should be, right?
If my static type is B, I cannot have a dynamic type A.
Yes.
Right.
Because, it has to be more specific.
So A is less specific.
So yeah, your intuition's correct.
Yeah.
What happens here if I change val A s array a?
Here I have, oh, that's the original code, it's always that.
And then I change that to, oh and if I do array b null null,
if I put my two elements null null.
So the one we did here won't compile at line two, right?
Because you can't instantiate a's and store them as b's, right?
this one will, I'll still be able to compile line two because null is
perfectly valid as a reference to a B, right? And then if I tried to do new C
there, that should work because a C is a B, so you can store it. And then the next
one though, line 4 will fail, right? Why will line 4 fail? Same reason, right? I
can't construct an a and store it as a reference to some subtype of a.
That's not allowed. So this solution strategy is essentially what we did.
Remember that the subtyping the relationship is reflexive. That just means
Anything is a subtype of itself.
So you have to ask the question about, is c a subtype of a?
Well, c is a subtype of b, and b is a subtype of a.
And so we said this has a transitive property.
We said that.
So that's that one.
So that was.
Let's look at number 28.
This is from week 7.
Start pressing the page down because that's the fastest one.
There it is.
There it is, 28, all right.
So this is on scope and lifetime.
We're jumping around now.
OK.
So let's look at this Scala code.
We have our function, or maybe it's our method, f.
It takes an x, which is an int, and returns an int.
It's going to then multiply x by 2 and store it in y.
It's going to use type inference here,
so this will end up being an int, right?
And then we'll add x plus y and then add z.
So which of the variables is free in f?
Is X free?
No, X is not free, Y is X not free.
Where is it defined?
So it's when you invoke the method, you get X.
What about Y, is that free?
No, it's defined here.
What's its type?
Int.
I said that before.
It's talking out loud.
Then I'm going to return x plus y plus z.
Is z free?
Yes.
So the meaning for z comes from some context outside of the library.
And that gets passed in what?
What's the term for the environment?
Closure.
So under the covers the compiler will create some class for you that
receive a value for z from some environment.
So the only variable that's free is z.
So we think it's d.
So only variable x is free, false.
x is not free.
All variables in f are bound, false.
They're not bound.
They're bound eventually at runtime from closure.
But they're not bound here.
If only variable y is free, false.
Only variable z, yes.
Variable x and z are free.
It's only z.
So it's d, and that is the answer.
So that one wasn't hopefully too hot.
Let's look at number 15.
More closures, okay.
So we have this definition f with a nested function g, and we get this expression f passing
the lists of one and two.
So what is x, what is the type of x going to be?
What we call f with that argument?
X is what?
A.
What's A?
Oh, int, sorry.
I couldn't hear you.
I heard A.
No, int, you're absolutely right, int, right.
So x becomes int for that invocation, right?
And let's see, so what does our function do?
So our function takes our list of whatever, so in our case, we have a list of ints, and
it's, oh, it's going to produce a list of, list of x and string.
Okay.
So then we have g.
So then we, okay, so we take our list of ints, and then we map it over g, and that actually
means we're calling g, right?
We're using curating, right?
So we're going to take g, I'm sorry, we're going to take xs, and each element's going
gonna be passed into G, right?
And what does G do?
Well, G says, all right,
I'm gonna take my initial list again
and map over that list,
and for each element, I'm gonna call to string.
I'm actually going to, what does this actually do?
Is there a way to express that in English?
I would start by saying it's gonna take each element
of excess and pair it with...
Is that the right way to say?
So I'm gonna take each element of excess,
which is an X, and I'm going to map it to a list of...
Each element of excess, I'm sorry, of excess
with the two string representation of it.
So it's sort of weird, right?
So I'm going to, I'm going to, for each one,
this is weird because we sort of throw it away, right?
Oh right, no, we don't throw it away, we map.
So we have x there, and this gets confusing because of all the x's, right?
We're using, right, so we're keeping this x, this lowercase x, right?
So if I have 1, 2, then first I'm going to call that with 1,
and then I'm going to then go through the original list
again, right?
And I'm going to bind to y, so I'm
going to stringify each element of y, so I'm going to have 1.
So for that first one, well, I'm going to just draw these out, so I have one, one, and two, two, three.
And then I'm going to now reiterate through excess, and I'm going to say,
I'm going to call toString on each element, so now I'm going to have one, two,
and this is a tuple, right?
Everybody see that?
So I think I'm going to end up with a list of lists
Oh, right.
Exactly.
One, two.
Oh, but why is this two, one here?
That's D.
So you're saying C.
Oh, okay, right.
One, one.
One, two.
Two, one.
Two, two.
Yeah, that's right.
All of those quotes and parentheses are like swimming.
It looks like permutation.
Yeah, yeah, it's, yes.
So, let's be, let's make sure it compiles.
I think it does.
From looking at it, I don't see anything that's not going to compile.
Confirm your understanding when studying.
I have to delete all these silly lineups.
I love how we're using like, oh, this code just uses the braces.
It doesn't use the bracelets syntax.
It uses braceful syntax, as some people might say.
But yeah, if I do that, so now the code compiles.
So if I call flist 12, yeah, that's what I get.
And notice that the REPL is giving you these and
these are actually strings, right?
We know that from the signature.
But the way that REPL prints it out, it doesn't put the quotes there.
So, the answer is c and I have…
That's c, very good.
So, if we look at the variations…
So
To make it a little smaller
it's not too small
So we're gonna in this variation. We're gonna change this so that's
this line three, right?
We're gonna change it to
Xs.map y, y to string.
Right, so in that case then we wouldn't be printing the x's,
the x values.
And here we have.
Here we would be, instead of strings, we'd be,
the other parameter would be an int, right?
That one would fail to compile, wouldn't it?
Why not?
With it?
Signature for f says it should be a string, but
if it's just x and y then it's returning list list of int, int.
Right, the signature, right, you're very astute.
So the type here is string variable here.
We're fixed, the type is fixed, the string.
So let's just confirm that.
I'm very sure that you're right here.
Oh, you know what, I can just do this.
So I'm changing this line to the tuple x, y, right?
And never mind that brace being on the wrong line, it doesn't matter with braces.
So there we go.
Yes, doesn't compile.
So various.
That's 15 across that one.
Let's do number 24.
C code!
Our old friend!
So the question is, which lines result in undefined order of operations on variable x?
So, this line's okay, right?
We're just declaring x and assigning it.
This line's okay, we're taking x,
incrementing one,
and assigning x to have that new value.
Here, we increment x, and then add one,
and then store it in x.
And here, we increment x,
and then what value of x do we use for this one?
Should that execute first or not?
So, which lines do you think stick out at you as resulting in an undefined
order of operations based on what we talked about?
Line three is okay, right?
We don't have line two as an option.
Line five is clearly weird, right, because we're referring to x over here.
We don't have a sequence point.
Remember the whole discussion on sequence points.
The answer key that I have says that the answer for 24 is d.
lines four and five.
So that must mean that the increment is not defined.
The increment, it isn't defined whether the increment happens after accessing x here or
after executing this expression here.
That's what's not defined.
So I had to think about that one because when I first looked at it I was like, really?
Because I thought that it would increment this, it would access X, increment X, and I don't care because it would have incremented that, and then I would have updated X anyway.
But according to the definition of C, it may be after this statement executes that X gets incremented.
So it might compile but it might not do what you expect.
Sorry, expect.
I can't think of my words by saying .
All right.
That's 24.
Okay.
So if we change, what happens if we change x plus plus plus one to x plus plus comma x equals x plus one?
That changes this line so that it's fine.
Because the comma is the sequence operator.
So by getting that sequence operator in there,
you evaluate this.
You do the increment.
And then you add one and set x equal to with it.
I'm not sure about this here.
Because it looks like it's still, oh right.
But in C, if you have this, I think the value of this.
This whole expression is gonna be the second thing after the sequence operation.
So then the value of this would be, so if we started with one,
we increment this to two, and we'll execute in this order.
So that's two, and now x is equal to three,
and the value of this whole thing is three,
so x would end up getting three plus one, four.
You'd have to play around in the compiler for that.
So that's 24.
Let's look at 10.
Uh, 10, we'll go back to last,
chapter 10.
Okay, so class A and then class B extends A.
a, substantiate b, our static type is b, our dynamic type is b, and then my static type
of y is going to be a and I'm going to take whatever b holds and refer to it.
Now it's being referred to as an a. So if I try to call, let's see, print x dot f1,
Well, it should dispatch to here.
x.f2 should dispatch to here.
And y.f1 will dispatch to which one?
Class B.
One in class B.
This is like the same thing we do at the beginning of class
tonight, right?
It's dispatching to the runtime type definition.
Alright, so what gets printed?
Well, five plus super f1,
so super f1 gives me one, so I should get six.
And then x dot f2, five plus,
what's going to be?
Oh, sorry, x dot f2, right, is 11, so six is 11, right.
And then y dot f1, so that should dispatch to there,
So we should print six, 611.6.
I forgot the question number.
It's 10 C.
611.6.
That's right.
We've got three minutes left, so I think we'll probably stop there.
So next week, we'll spend most of our time working through this stuff.
Please call out questions as you have them.
I appreciate that some of you are doing that.
It does illustrate things for everybody, so do ask your questions in the public forum.
We're all learning, well, you're all learning this stuff.
I'm learning the JavaScript stuff over and over again.
Still not like it.
But JavaScript does things weird.
And one of the goals of this class
is to give you the working knowledge
you need to make sense of the language when it gets thrown.
All right.
Thanks.
See you next week.
We need to cut the knife out.
so
and
I'll enjoy javascript.
I will try my best, we'll see. Maybe this time I'll like it, no, I don't know.
You'll never give me to like it.
Yeah, I agree.
I see wanting to be a full stack developer, but I just cannot like JavaScript.
So the whole, the whole, it's such a, it's so stupid.
So the whole reason why full stack, I'm going to tell you my perspective.
The whole reason why full stack developer is a thing is because, um,
developers are not cheap and small companies when they hire people,
they want them to be able to basically do that.
And this is the historical sort of like perspective.
So like I work in large enough companies that we all pretty much specialize.
it's pretty well accepted at a large enterprise institution like my company that the kinds
of problems that you run into and the depth of knowledge needed to solve them is...
If you're good at UI, you're probably not, you haven't focused on back-end stuff as much
in your career.
at backend stuff, you probably haven't focused on UI stuff that much in your career.
That's the full stack.
So, smaller companies that were startups during tech booms, they're like, well, we've got
to hire people, and we've got to hire people to be full stack.
Then that morphed into DevOps.
Well, yeah, DevOps.
Right.
So, you want me to be an expert at whatever deployment infrastructure du jour.
That's what you want.
But I focus on this stuff.
And it's sort of like at a larger company, I can kind of get away with having other people
do most of the bulk of that.
I mean, I still have to get stuff deployed, right?
But I don't have to become an expert on Jenkins or that was the thing ten years ago.
Jenkins was the big build system.
The big thing that ran your continuous integration.
Like, yeah, I'm not going to become an expert on stuff.
I'm an expert on programming languages.
That's what I focus on.
To say otherwise is slightly insulting.
A large enterprise is going to need all of those things and different people specialize
in different ways.
Honestly I think the people who specialize in this stuff are the ones who are able to
understand it.
Not everybody's able to understand this stuff.
I'm not trying to put anybody down, of course, but like the people that,
um,
the people that specialize in this stuff are able to solve more complex problems.
And that's not a denigration of those people.
It's just like,
like this is my specialty and I have the ability to spend my time thinking about
it. So I specialize in this.
That makes sense.
Yeah.
And it's much more complicated than UI.
Well, UI is very complicated, as you saw with this JavaScript.
Almost nobody deals with JavaScript directly.
These layers are complicated.
JavaScript's like the operating system for the browser.
Yeah, so it's like C for browsers?
Yeah.
Yeah, it's that low level sort of thing.
But, yeah, I never specialized in that.
And I didn't want to, because I liked the big computer science problems.
Like, back in the day, like having to deal with large amounts of data coming through a system,
processing a large amount of data, and how do we scale those systems, right?
And the answer to how we scale the systems has changed over the years, right?
So it's been fun to keep up with all that.
That's what I keep up with.
I don't keep up with Jenkins or GitHub Actions or Terraform or any of the crap they use.
That's serious.
Yes, same here.
I don't know a little.
Any of this stuff.
That's the wrong one.
Yeah.
Well, see you next week.
Yeah, see you next week.
Good luck with JavaScript.
Yeah.
Hopefully it won't be too awful.
No. No, we'll see.
I'll let you know if you have any questions.
Alright.
See you next week, 2.
I don't know.
Thank you.
All right.
So, let's move on.
.
Thank you.
Okay.
.
Thank you.
So, we have the new one.
And so it was hard. It was hard to find them in a transition.
I want to see you.